Okay, we are now going to call over the council meeting for today's day and time out
in two of the public input and unscheduled personal appearances in one of the answer, which
is to address the council on any of the agenda items.
There are being not out of three as a consent agenda staff and it's recommending items four
through 16 for the consent agenda, if there are no questions on any of those items,
so we have a motion to approve and a second.
Second, go call please.
So it's in four states, Western, I, Lewis, I chose.
Aye, item, is that it is for 16, I have 17 is City Posture Agreement Beach and
this contract for fiscal year 2017, 2018.
Do we have a motion to approve?
Second, roll call please.
Aye, Lewis, I, Western, Johnson, Schultz.
Aye, item 18 is the member item of understanding to incorporate article 33-29.
Handle program is part of the collective bargaining agreement for July 11, 2016,
through June 30, 2018, between the city of Miami and the fraternal
order, police lodged number 121, and authorizes the manager of sign.
And we've got Dean and Chief Anderson and Kim Allis, too.
Well, I'll go ahead and kick it off and I think it's chief and Kim.
I want to come and also I want to recognize that we have members of large 21 here as well.
So we're one, oh, excuse me, 21.
So let me go ahead and kick this off as to what we're doing.
You might remember, gosh, Chief Anderson was about eight or nine months ago.
We received an anonymous donation and it was for the betterment of the, my, my, a police department.
And it was basically it was anonymous.
We had no idea.
And then just few days later, the Peoria tribe matched the donation.
Chief Anderson called, matched that.
So at that time, we made it very clear that the money was not going to supplant anything that we already had in the budget for the
minor police department.
And that Chief Anderson was going to kind of consider some various things that may not have made it in the budget
that we would be able to utilize the money's for.
And I think there are a lot of very good ideas, but I want to compliment Chief Anderson,
because he talked to the rank and file and really came up with the idea that the minor police department
needs a canine, a canine office.
And that is what we're talking about today that the monies that we're donated to us and I hope that whoever donated kind of keeps up with us and watches us in the media and all that because we don't know who it is.
So we want them to know that if it wasn't for this donation we wouldn't be talking about bringing in K9 officer on board for the city of Miami.
And we're very grateful for that.
We had a very good process with the FOP because when you're talking about a K9 officer, especially for the K9 it's a lifetime appointment.
The K9 will probably be in service for about 10 years.
And that K9 then is assigned to an officer and they basically form a bond.
There's not a situation, it's not a pet, but this is going to be a police officer.
And it's a bond and it's a lifetime bond.
So until that until that K9 officer crosses the Rainbow Bridge, they're together even when the K9 officer retires.
So we have a process that we're bringing you today to approve.
And that is to have a process by which we have a K9 officer, how we select the K9 officer, how we compensate the K9 officer.
So from that, I'd like to turn it over to the chief.
We didn't have to donate money.
We wanted to, we held that for a little bit to make sure we did the best way we could do the same.
We had several suggestions and several ideas and several options came to me with the K9 option.
And I want to thank officer, and I want to be a very persistent on the K9 issue.
And I said, all right, well, you know, give me the paperwork right.
He wrote up all these procedures.
Did all the legwork on and did a great job.
And I told him a lot of those.
I thank you very much for doing that.
And I do think it's the best way to serve my environment.
It's a great use of donate funds.
And then to the city and the lodge, make agreements.
We do have the application process for that position.
And then the policy procedure.
And everything needed to compensation, the handler and the handle of the dog.
Chief, can you go over how the dog will be used?
It will be a controllable primary degree drug dog control dog.
I've been able to use for introduction or any control functions throughout the department.
It's something that's definitely needed in the area.
Currently, the quantum marshals have worked with our area.
That we call them we need.
But it's limited and hard to get.
BIA in the past had a working dog and they're kind of off on.
And it's just it's kind of hard to get dogs in the area.
This reach of the country is.
Now, for narcotics of math, and we're trying to do it, and we're trying to help it, and we're
having to come about to that.
I think this is just a big great step.
A great way to help our citizens market.
Is this a dog of the use possibly schools?
Yes.
If they call it...
We've had a couple businesses called, say, hey, is there any way we can get a dog to walk through?
You know, they're wanting to give it a drive for businesses, head once a day.
We're working on trying to get them where you would try to get their dog to your business.
So, that's how we'll be able to take care of ourselves, and we'll be able to do that.
We've used canned reform schools.
We'll be able to do that.
Question.
So, it'll be a very much for us to know what to do.
What's the procedure for others?
Changing the officer and where did they go to training with this dog?
We do have an application process.
We're going to apply and then have an interview order.
We're going to solicit some came-off system here to assist us with that order.
I'm sorry, but I came to an officer, been around for several years.
But as far as what the needs are and what the strain is on the officer,
who better than did guys that do that for living and have dogs.
So, we've asked some of our area in Oxford to help us with that interview process.
Just so whoever we have apply is fully aware of what we need to do.
Because that dog's a little of them, become with them, and it's a full time commitment.
So, we want to make sure at least that they're aware of the exact nature of that commitment.
We have some officers that have done that, helps in that.
And we have current, we're looking at a train school,
as they've got those things.
Patriot Town.
They offered so far the best product of training, followed training.
And then an animal team training.
They have to go through growth.
And then they get certified in that kind of stage to be certified to the stage.
It is all costly, but then products very much open.
And not only is it a situation of selecting the officer,
but also the reason for this amendment is that there will be a change of compensation for that officer that's selected as well.
But then that officer has responsibilities to take care of the animal.
I guess that's my concern, just because I'd like to be educated a little bit more on it.
With this canine, and it's going to be with this officer from this point on what's it selected.
That's right.
What age is this canine been used before?
with other officers?
It's a new case.
Is it a new case?
Of course it.
They'll be trained together.
It came.
There's certain age of a dog before they turn it trained within.
Yes.
Okay.
The early year old.
We'll start training.
And where they're kept and with what that officer is those guidelines?
Yeah.
We'll have their best practices for that.
So we can go there.
Not that I'm saying they have our officers.
We know that.
But I've just, there's guidelines that that dog has to live a certain.
Okay.
That's what I'm going to do.
Yeah.
Because once those, once the officer in the dog formed that law, that dog can't go to another
course.
Right.
So it's very quick.
But I'm just talking like living.
Right.
There are entities from that dog or sir.
Yes.
Part of the fines are going to go to for a dog run for shelter bed.
That kind of stuff.
And then back here.
So it's.
Is there a grain for something in the future that can be written for any form of,
a aid or something for it in the future?
Like next year, you just want to.
I'm assuming you budget in for.
We know.
We've had a few organizations and individuals say that they would love to continue finding
on the program.
And I know that I know.
I know.
I have a thought several people that have been very interested in and
want to program dog and offer the systems.
I can only imagine.
Yeah.
And I know it's the next agenda item that we're going to be adding a police officer.
No.
The.
That is the police officer.
Oh, okay.
That's it.
One of.
It may seem.
No.
I understand now.
Well, I think for the record.
I think it's good that we pointed out that the main reason for doing that is,
as our city attorney mentions to this estate law as well.
That dog is going to be a police officer.
Right.
And if the dog has any injuries or any five minutes.
Or if anybody causes injury through that dog.
It's as though they caused injury to a law enforcement officer.
And I think it's very important.
So for FTEs, I wanted to make sure that even the record shows that we've added,
we've added an additional FTE.
And if it's that.
Okay.
That dog.
Yes.
You will bring the dog up and you're reducing to everyone.
Yeah.
You're probably checking your problem.
Hey, we're going to vote now.
That the community I've served in as we've had a canine.
That's the most loved police officer in town.
Sorry guys, but.
I know we had a German shepherd and there was no way that E.M.
I was going to get in our house.
And she just became too big and they're great jogger.
I guess it is going to be a German shepherd.
That's probably, yeah.
They're good. Good.
They're good. They're good.
So do you have certain-
officers, have you said you had certain officers put into want to do this?
As soon as this is approved, I'm going to post that.
I'm going to have to pay for that.
I was soon that one of them said right here, so I'm going to do this probably.
Of course, I'm going to do a five.
You have done a majority of work on this.
I won't buy it.
You did a great job put it together.
I'm very proud of it.
His efforts.
And I've said probably the first one put together.
Or put it to a flat board.
I know it talked with a couple others, but considered it in our company.
That was absolutely who is really interested in that.
You might be talking maybe about three months on.
You're looking at getting the dog and service or...
As soon as we can get it out of the app,
I would soon pretty much be pretty close to that.
Okay.
I'm excited.
Thank you.
Great addition to the city.
And not only that, but again, I just want to reiterate the teamwork that took place with the police department.
You know, gift like this allowed something that may not have been able to make the budget.
But that doesn't mean that it's not an important thing.
And again, getting together and deciding what would be best for the department and what would be best for my Emma.
I think it was a very good process on very proud of you.
Okay.
So, do we have a motion to approve either mate team?
I'll make that motion.
And the second?
Well second.
Roll call please.
Lewis.
I Weston.
Aye.
Forster.
Johnson.
So.
And then I am 19 years related, which is increasing FTEs by one from 1997 to allow for the additional
The K9.
And second.
Roll call.
Johnson.
I Weston.
Aye.
Forster.
So.
All right.
Thanks, Chief.
Thank you guys very much for your work on it.
I'm going to thank the great addition.
I thank you.
Item 19 is new business.
Any new business?
Item 20 is new business.
Staff reports eh.
Staff available.
If you have any questions.
Twenty-two mayré counsel from you.
An announcements.
Any announcements.
I'd like to, thank all the cities too.
The ones who are in the rodeo on the first time and second time around.
I don't know or ensume them.
But it was telling a good rodeo.
And every action would be even better.
Uh AD major communication being?
Well what I'd like to also mention that state representatives moring.
provided a number of rodeo tickets for city employees in the city.
always greatly enjoyed that. And I wanted to thank state representatives
lowering for that. So a lot of people got to take in the rodeo and really
appreciated that. Three announcements. One, I wanted to give a Eagle picture
update for the demolition. You do know that we reported in the past that they
did discover more chat in that area than they anticipated. We knew we were going
to have chat just more chat. So they've gone through a the change order for the
demolition contractor to properly remove the chat. Has been approved by the
state. They still need to approve the contractor that's going to be
monitoring the air quality while that is being taken place. We think that
will take place next week. And we believe that right after that they'll get back
to finishing off that demolition. And then after the demolition we get
started on the splash pan. So I wanted to give an update on why that's
held off. If somebody drives by and wonders what's taking place, the state has to
go through that process for the change orders for the additional chat. O-DOT is
going to be starting resurfacing on A Street, North East and North West. If you
notice, there's a reader board on Main Street regarding that. And that's a long
way to project where that's going to be read done. And I'm just talking to a
leisure contractor. They're still doing the for the microsurfacing. They're still
doing the crack ceiling. And once that's done, and once the crack ceiling is
cured and once we've inspected to make sure it's okay, then we will be starting
microsurfacing soon. So we'll be too much longer before people start to see
asphalt being laid in my Amazon. So that's a good thing there. And then finally, in
Mayer, you probably would want to be part of this announcement, but really with
Mayer's assistance and also with state representative loings of assistance with
state-centred abortions assistance, we have started an additional dialogue
right now with O-DOT about the 125 bridge. You might remember that you approved in
agreement with us with all synonyssosciates that in 2018 the 125 bridge is
going to start being redact. And that means that it's going to be closed. And in my
two and a half years here, we've had to close state highway 125 times because
of high water. It's just a continual situation. And we approach the state about
could they approach move and raise the approaches onto the state highway. And the
word we got back was they did not have the funding for it. But it's still going to
be probably the best opportunity to do that that we've ever had. So with the
groups that have come together and we've also brought in auto-counting and we've
also brought in the Cherokee Nation. And we've we're coming up with a plan right now
in which this project might still be done with local resources and with some assistance
from O-DOT. So one of the things
that we are wanting to make sure of is that if we do this, number one, we'll have permission
from ODOT to do it.
We can't just go on to a state highway and do a project like this.
We'd have to coordinate.
Since this project is going to be let, I believe this probably is coming far.
We need to talk to ODOT about the potential dates on which this project will be let, because
if we're going to be raising the approaches of the flood area, we're going to have to take
care of a number of different processes through the federal guidelines on flooding, FEMA, things
such as the half that takes a bit of time, but also some engineering.
And it's going to require us to do some engineering.
So we have been talking with Sean about not the entire 45,000 that you have already approved,
but at least starting some initial engineering work on this project that we can show to ODOT
to get them to understand what the scope of this project is to be able to start working on that.
And I think it's very important.
As I said, we have just one shot of doing this.
I know that people will say, well, they're priorities too, but when you consider that five times
in the last two and a half years, one quarter of our town has been cut off, where people are
having to detour.
This is an important project for our future.
And we're getting started.
I just want to add, we also, I guess, the center part of this group of people is Grand Gateway
and Ed Crone and his people, and Ed's trying to coordinate all the different potential contributors
to this project, and GODA is also a potential contributor in one or two different ways,
and so we hope that they do decide up this way.
The decision point we're really at right now is we budgeted to 45,000, but then we decided
to say, hold off and not spend any of it yet, because we didn't know how this project was going on before.
The challenge that Ed has is, he has to know, how much money do we need before he can start going to the church,
he tried, where the city or grant funds or whatever, and figure out what that number is, and then start looking for matching grant.
And so after that, we had Dean and I talked and said, we probably need to go back to the council at this point,
and talk about spending some of that money, just to come up with what the cost is going to be, because otherwise Ed can start asking,
when you say, I need some money, but you don't know how much.
It's hard to hear about it, come here.
That's kind of really where we are, and I don't know if Sean has been able to give you any indication, Dean,
of the preliminary number one at my hospital, but we basically what we're asking the council is to approve
to start spending some of that money, not all other than some of it, just to get an idea what the cost is going to be,
so that Ed can go to work on our behalf.
putting in the different pools of money to get it.
So, and Sean, I don't know how much dollar you and Dean have had since that meaning
if you even have a ballpark.
We've started a little bit just more groundwork stuff just getting, we've got to propose
my offer for FEMA for your new A-mas, that's supposed to be kind of needed to pay extra.
And the way is to use that model and then start looking at what the I-way needs to be done with
looking at structures we need to put under it because this works when we get in a flood plan.
So, we can't change that flood elation for what they established that.
And the starting point is what we need to do through the thing we start working on costs for that.
Hopefully start getting granted.
If we initially thought it was going to be 45,000 to design the whole project.
Is that the third description of what we thought the 45,000 would be?
Okay.
45 was a piece of business model.
And figure out what we need to do in the project.
And then you can probably accept your time.
You won't probably go that far with it.
Okay.
So, are you telling me that to give us the information we need to provide the grant gateway that we probably need to
spend the 45,000 or is there some number less than that?
Actually, I think it's less than 45, I think, 43.
Maybe what that would be.
It's not 20.
I was hoping that we had an hour of a contract like the rest of our work.
So, as long as we guys work on it through the work, we can do that in our work.
So, I guess I'll revise my statement.
We're not asking you to consider screening some of that money.
It's not like we're asking.
We're going to send it to Georgia.
But we still have to get an idea because it's changed a little bit from when you originally gave us permission.
But we still, that amount of money is budgeted.
And we're thinking we're going to need to start getting into that to get this done.
And I have to say, there's no guarantee that Ed and Cherokee did we all going to be able to come up with one of the amount of money as it we need.
But there's no real way to start until we know what that comes from.
And I feel optimistic about it, especially with the county being on board.
Because there's going to be a lot of kind of labor and keep the cost down.
But until we know how big that pool of money is, we can't really go step first.
And if we get permission from ODOT to do it, we're going to have to do it to ODOT standards.
So, therefore, we're going to have to make sure there's properly designed to engineer it and watch this.
I think that was my concern when we talked about this last.
And I think I brought up the situation and set forward in the communication between the county and the state.
in that and how there's an ordeal or situation currently out there and my concern was
that I don't want into that situation and so it led me to believe what's our second option
and I think it was mentioned that if they were going to do it or if we was ever going to have the
state do all that on their own it might push the bridge project back a year or two if that's
and if that is an option I would like to know if they're saying no we don't have the funding in 2018
I think it was the year 2018 is what they have they're saying no but we could do it in 2019 the whole thing
or 20 I'd like to know that I mean I know it's $45,000 maybe more maybe less but if they're I would
just like to know the dialogue with the state if they say now wait I and I'm kind of almost no
where you're going to go with it and I'm going to trust me my wife's a teacher I know the state
doesn't have any money but I just with that money that we're putting out there if it's two years later
three years later I don't know how I don't know the condition if the bridge can make it two
years I'm going to keep it. We did ask the state because we were afraid that already let the contract
if they had been basically it was going to happen in 2018 and it wasn't nothing we could do about it
except for face the fact that they may have to close it down again later that's what we're really trying
to avoid the fact that they haven't let the contract get as good for us and then it gives us some flexibility
but it also means we need to move forward so that we can try to coordinate or face the
prospect of being shut down for you and then turn around maybe not very long after that and shutting it
down again or having to close the road chronically because of flooding or that. Yeah I wish I wish there
was a better answer but I don't think that there is. You want to have anything been and you think
positive to have to have that? It's a positive positive here to help realistically I mean they're
going to do the dead that's whether it's going to be in 18 or 19 or so as far as raising the approaches
it's not on the eight year plan it may never happen unless we make it unless we make it happen
and we're working with Stuart for example to get it on the eight year plan that's that's uh that is an
important step and then once it's on the plan then they can kind of move it around a little bit and maybe
you trade and say well you know this project maybe is a higher priority for our county than this one they don't
like to move money out of counties but if you're within a county and you know they may say well we can
hold off on this for a year to do this. There's a little bit of horse trading that can be done but not
lock. So what you're saying like this is probably our best chance to have something done out there.
It's a gamble. It's our best chance I think.
And would you think that's fair or statement meant to, from the state's point of view?
And the nice thing about this is everybody else that we've been working with.
There's a real candy latitude to try to make it happen.
So I think everybody's going to try to work very hard because they're recognized in the fact that this is a necessity.
Well, not me, I don't want to spend a quarter by that time with me.
I'd like me.
I don't really spot that chance to get that done out there.
Well, I think it's too important.
I don't want to start and start and stop.
I'm going to project that.
A, I mean, for safety sites, we've been able to fire and all that.
I can see the benefit of getting one project done all at once.
Well, economic development too, there's, you know, issues with that.
Yeah.
Getting in and out of the city at certain times.
So, you know, there's been a problem.
Any questions about speaking?
Okay.
So, um, we've already approved the expenditure.
Dean, are you just looking?
I think they say move forward.
The key thing is, is the last time we reported to you as we just said we're going to hold off.
Because Oda said they don't have money.
Now, we've got this project going.
You've already authorized this before we started doing it.
We wanted to make sure you knew what was going on.
Okay.
So, if you have 45, I think it was 45 that was budgeted and can maintain.
So, that's there.
Yeah.
Anything else to do in under city management communication?
No, that's it.
Okay.
Next item is the executive session.
For 21 to 25 OOS 3071.
For all the reasons listed in that agenda item.
And do you have a statement you want to make?
Yes.
Mr. Mayor, in regards to the third executive,
executive session item, which is in regards to the two lawsuits,
would be my recommendation that that needs to be discussed in,
in an executive session as a public disclosure,
would not be in the best interests in the city.
Okay.
So, the rule of law of thinking,
we have a motion going executive session for the reasons that
they outlined and that are listed on the agenda item 24.
I'd like to vote for that.
And a second.
Thank you.
We'll call both.
Johnson.
Uh-huh.
For Mr. Weston.
Hi.
Mr. Johnson.
And we're actually going to take a short break.
And we're going to re-continue upstairs.